Register of the Boris Petrovich Lopatin papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Boris Petrovich Lopatin papers
1909-1943
2018C12
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet)
Writings, notes, diaries, biographical data, and printed matter, relating to the Russian Civil War in Siberia, Russian émigré affairs, and world politics in the interwar period.
Lopatin, Boris Petrovich, b. 1876.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2017.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical note
Russian journalist, subsequently émigré in the United States.
Biographical Chronology
1876 17 April Born, Lomga, Poland, Russian Empire
1910 15 May Graduates
1905 Participates in the Russo-Japanese War as an artillery officer
1909 Married Agata Sergeevna
1912 War correspondent for the newspaper Den’ during the Balkan War
1914-1917 Called to arms as a captain, serves on the Galician and Hungarian fronts, wounded, promoted to the rank of Lt. Colonel, resigns at the outbreak of the 1917 revolution
1915 29 August Birth of son Oleg in Petrograd
1918 Founds and edits the Vladivostok newspapers Moia gazeta and Ekho
1919 July Ekho closed and Lopatin is arrested
1921 August Reopens Ekho newspaper
1922 Moved to Harbin, China, and Japan
1923 24 February Arrived in San Francisco with wife and son
1923 9 March-June Editor of Russkaia zhizn’ newspaper
1923 17 June Moves to Berkeley
1932 Led an art class for children
1933-1934 Art director for the Hollywood Playhouse
1935 Taught art and interior decorating at Fremont High School
1943 27 May Died, Los Angeles, California
1906-1914 Begins work as a professional newspaperman and edits newspapers Rus” (St. Petersburg), Russkoe slovo (Moscow), and Den’ (St. Petersburg)
Scope and Contents note
The papers, consisting of biographical documents, correspondence, diaries, writings, photographs and printed matter reflect life in pre-revolutionary Russia, the turmoil of revolution and civil war, and the subsequent lives of Russians who found themselves emigrants in the United States.
Boris Lopatin had a great deal of experience as a newspaper correspondent and editor before the 1917 Russian Revolution, during the subsequent civil war, and attempted to continue his journalistic career in the United States.
His writings reflect his socialist political sympathies and devote much attention to growing tensions in Europe and East Asia in the 1930s, the political and economic developments in the Soviet Union, and the start of World War II.
Arrangement Statement
The collection is organized into 7 series: Biographical file, Correspondence, Diaries, Writings, Subject file, Printed matter, and Photographs.
Journalists.; Russia. Emigration and immigration.; Siberia (Russia)--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; World politics--1900-1945
- Biographical file, 1917-1941 and undated. (Box-folder 1)
  Address book, autobiography, calling cards, certificates, family file, medical records, naturalization records, writings about him, and miscellany arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Address book, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Autobiography, undated [ca 1934]. (Box-folder 1: 2)
    An autobiographical essay and a letter of application for a correspondent position
  - Calling cards, undated (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Certificates, 1917 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    Residence certificate and voter registration certificate for elections of the All Russian Constituent Assembly
  - Family file (Box-folder 1)
    - Lopatin, Oleg Borisovich (son), 1937 (Box-folder 1: 5)
      Typescript of untitled story or essay.
    - Lopatina, Agata Sergievna (wife) (Box-folder 1)
      - Biographical, 1917-1928. (Box-folder 1: 6)
        Voter registration certificate for elections of the All Russian Constituent Assembly and copies of naturalization papers
      - Diary, undated. (Box-folder 1: 7)
        Holograph.
      - Diary, 1915-1916. (Box-folder 1: 8)
        Typescript. Contains notes about the birth of her son Oleg and the first months of his life.
      - Correspondence, 1941 (Box-folder 1: 9)
      - Writings, 1941 and undated. (Box-folder 1: 10)
        Holograph and typescript. Impressions of viewing Charlie Chaplin’s movie “The Great Dictator” and a notebook of various drafts
      - Miscellany, undated. (Box-folder 1: 11)
        Verse written for her son Oleg (“Lel’”) by Boris Beta and Arsenii Nesmelov as well as verse dedicated to her
  - Medical records, 1919-1941 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Naturalization records, 1923-1928 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Writings about him, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    Statement by Hector J. Boon regarding the closing of the newspaper Ekho and the arrest of its editor B. P. Lopatin
  - Miscellany, 1930 and undated. (Box-folder 1: 15)
    Contains an exhibit catalog of works by members of The United Scenic Artists of America (includes 6 works by Lopatin), a description of one of his works, a drawing of a house, a letter of introduction from United Artists Studio Corp., a contractor’s license, a list of agents, and an advertisement for furnished apartments and rooms in Paris
- Correspondence, 1917-1938 and undated. (Box-folder 1: 16)
  General correspondence arranged chronologically. Includes letters from friends and relatives as well as letters to and from publishers
- Diaries, 1915-1941. (Box-folder 1)
  All the entries from 1915-1923 are devoted to his son Oleg.
  - Diary, 1915-1926 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Diary, 1916-1917 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Diary, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Diary, 1919-1923 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Diary, 1940-1941. (Box-folder 1: 21)
    Also includes newspaper clippings as well as entries about B. P. Lopatin’s medical problems and their treatment
- Writings, 1919-1943 and undated (Box-folder 1-4)
  Writings arranged chronologically by title.
  - “The Converted: A One Act Play,”, undated.
    - Complete text. typescript (Box-folder 1: 22)
    - Drafts of scenes II and III. Holograph and typescript (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - “Dvazhdy emigrant,” typescript, undated. (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Fragment (pages 5-8) of an essay about American women, typescript, undated. (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - “Herman from Bohemia,” holograph, undated. (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - “History of Art Sketched,” typescript, undated. (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - “How Can America Stay out of War,” typescript, undated. (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - “Igrushka,” typescript, undated. (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - “Il’ia Muromets, bogatyr’ russkii. (Skazanie),” holograph and typescript, undated. (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - “An Imaginary Interview,” holograph, undated. (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - “Mat’ i syn,” holograph, undated. (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - “Movie Directory Primary. Dedicated to Ignorabuses (sic!) of Hollywood,”holograph, undated. (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - “Nevostrebovannaia liubov’,” holograph, undated. (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - “Otkrytoe pis’mo Bludnomu Synu,” typescript, undated. (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Outline for a 4-act play about a Jewish family, holograph, undated. (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - “Paskha,” proofs, undated. (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - “The Passing Art of Old Japan,” typescript, Also includes a photograph of B. P. Lopatin and his family visiting painter Gihei Anayama (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - “Revolutionist in Exile: Story of Leon Trotsky,” typescript, undated. (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - “Sharmanka,” holograph, undated. (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - “Sokrat – revoliutsioner filisofskoi mysli,” holograph, undated. (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - “Stroiat,” holograph and typescript, undated. (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - “Tourists’ Reports on Russia,” holograph, undated. (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Untitled article (in Russian) on contemporary youth, typescript, undated. (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Untitled article on Manchuria, typescript, undated. (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Untitled autobiographical fragment covering the years 1896-1905, typescript and holograph, undated. (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - Untitled draft (part III) of a story about a lieutenant in the Russian Civil War in Siberia, holograph, undated. (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - Untitled essay on children’s complaints about their parents, holograph, undated. (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - Untitled first-person narrative of a young Jewish woman, holograph, also includes one page of typescript, undated. (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - Untitled list of questions about the outbreak of World War II, holograph, undated. (Box-folder 2: 27)
  - Untitled manuscript about a tiger hunt in the taiga, holograph, undated. (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - Untitled plot summary for a story, holograph, undated. (Box-folder 2: 29)
  - Untitled sketch about a visit to a poolroom, holograph, undated. (Box-folder 2: 30)
  - Untitled storyline about a lady-in-waiting and an officer of the Chevaliers Guard Regiment, Holograph. Russian text in pencil with English translation in pen on the reverse, undated. (Box-folder 2: 31)
  - “The War Furnace of Central Asia,” typescript., undated. (Box-folder 2: 32)
    Also includes a map “Sinkiang Province of China” drawn by B. P. Lopatin.
  - “What I had Seen and Heard in Hollywood,” holograph, undated. (Box-folder 2: 33)
  - “What is Poetry,” holograph, undated. (Box-folder 2: 34)
  - “What Next from Japan?” typescript, undated. (Box-folder 2: 35)
  - “Who is Encircling Whom?” typescript, undated. (Box-folder 2: 36)
  - Fragments of newspaper articles written during the Russian Civil War, clippings, [1918-1919]. (Box-folder 2: 37)
  - Untitled album of mounted clippings of articles under B. P. Lopatin’s pseudonyms S. Rokotov and B. Shuiskii, 1919 and undated (Box-folder 2: 38)
  - "Verse, Typescript. “A Farewell” and “Dedication to an Ending” ", undated. (Box-folder 2: 39)
  - “Kak tsarevich sdielalsia pomoshchnikom sadovnika,” holograph, undated [1922]. (Box-folder 2: 40)
  - “Skazka o chernoi sobakie,” holograph, 1922 (Box-folder 2: 41)
  - “Gandi I gandizm,” typescript, undated [1924]. (Box-folder 2: 42)
  - “Krest’iane i kommunizm,” typescript, 1924 (Box-folder 2: 43)
  - “Lenin,” typescript, 1924 (Box-folder 2: 44)
  - “Smert’ Lenina,” proofs, undated [1924]. (Box-folder 2: 45)
  - “Lev Tolstoi,” typescript and holograph, undated [1928]. (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Fragments of letters to editors, clippings, 1931-1932 and undated. (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - “Japan’s Future and U.S. Neutrality,” typescript, undated [1931]. (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - “Japanese Domination in Asia and the Pacific,” typescript, undated [1932]. (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - “Manchurian Vignettes. (From a War Correspondent’s Notebook),” typescript, undated [1932]. (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - “Oligarchy vs. Democracy in Asia,”typescript, undated [1932]. (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - “The Only Tsar Created by the Revolution,” typescript, undated [1932]. (Box-folder 3: 7)
    Also includes a photograph
  - “Russia’s Place in the Sino-Japanese Conflict,”typescript, undated [1932]. (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - “Strategy of Japan in the Far East,” holograph, undated [1932]. (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Croquis, 1933-1942. (Box-folder 3: 10)
    Eleven sketches (in Russian)
  - “What Can Prevent the Japanese Hegemony over the Pacific,” typescript, undated [1933]. (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - “Meaning of Russia’s F.Y.P. [Five Year Plan],” typescript, 1934 (Box-folder 3: 12)
    Also includes hand-drawn charts on industrial output and iron ore production
  - “Serge Soudeikine in Hollywood,” typescript, undated [1934]. (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - “The World’s Oldest Revolutionist,” typescript, undated [1934]. (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - Nabroski khudozhnika, 1936-1937 and undated.
    A series of sketches, which B. P. Lopatin also translated into English as Sketches En Route. (Reminiscences of a Hollywood Artist)
    - “Voprosy,” typescript, undated. (Box-folder 3: 15)
      Also includes “Questions,” typescript, undated.
    - “Ona poniala,” typescript, undated. (Box-folder 3: 16)
      Also includes “She Understood,” typescript, undated.
    - “Domik na gore,” typescript, undated. (Box-folder 3: 17)
    - “Dobraia Samaritianka,” typescript. (Box-folder 3: 18)
      Also includes “Good Samaritan,” typescript, undated.
    - “Piatistvol’nyi dub,” typescript, undated. (Box-folder 3: 19)
      Also includes “Live Oak,” typescript, undated.
    - “Vse lgut,” typescript, 1936 (Box-folder 3: 20)
      Also includes “Everybody Lies.”
    - “Piat’ korolev,” typescript, undated [1937]. (Box-folder 3: 21)
      Also includes “Five Queens,” typescript, undated.
    - “Farmer Dzhakson,” typescript, undated. (Box-folder 3: 22)
      Also includes “Jackson, the Farmer” typescript, undated.
    - “Kto vyigral?" typescript, undated. (Box-folder 3: 23)
      Also includes “Who Won?” holograph,, undated.
    - “B’iula,” typescript, undated. (Box-folder 3: 24)
    - “Lecture on Art,” typescript, undated. (Box-folder 3: 25)
  - “Meet Henry Matisse,” typescript, undated [1936]. (Box-folder 3: 26)
  - Untitled essay on Charlie Chaplin, typescript, undated [1936]. (Box-folder 3: 27)
  - Untitled essay on the Soviet Union, holograph, undated [1936]. (Box-folder 3: 28)
  - “Opyt politicheskikh obzorov,” typescript, 1938 (Box-folder 3: 29)
  - Untitled articles (in Russian) on Nazism, Communism, and the Tripartite Pact, typescript and holograph, 1938-1940. (Box-folder 3: 30)
  - “Ersatz,” typescript, undated [1939]. (Box-folder 3: 31)
  - “Honeymoon,” typescript, 1939 (Box-folder 3: 32)
    Also includes a holograph Russian text of this piece signed Agata Lopatina
  - “Malthus’ Follower,”, undated [1939]. (Box-folder 3: 33)
    Holograph (Russian original) and “A Follower of Malthus”, B. P. Lopatin’s English translation. The English version is in part written on the reverse of rejection letters from various publishers of Lopatin’s other articles
  - “Why the Soviet Russia – Germany Pact?”typescript, undated [1939]. (Box-folder 3: 34)
  - “We Shall Come Back: An Original Screen Treatment,” typescript, originally entitled “Tale of One Village,”, undated [1942]. (Box-folder 3: 35)
  - “Khorosho zadumannyi den’,”typescript and holograph, [1943]. (Box-folder 4: 1)
- Subject File, 1909-1939 and undated (Box-folder 4)
  Documents and printed matter arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Art –- European, undated. (Box-folder 4: 2)
    Notes prepared by B. P. Lopatin in Russian and English on European art from the Middle Ages to the 20th century
  - Artists -- Public opinion, undated. (Box-folder 4: 3)
    Notes prepared by B. P. Lopatin regarding a poll he took of thirteen individuals about artists
  - Dillinger, John, 1934 (Box-folder 4: 4)
    Clipping from the Los Angeles Examiner and notes by B. P. Lopatin
  - Koni, Fedor Alekseevich (1809-1879), 1909 (Box-folder 4: 5)
    Clipping from Niva magazine of article on the 100th anniversary of Koni’s birth
  - Poetry -- Russian and French, undated. (Box-folder 4: 6)
    Copies of verse by A. Polezhaev, F. Tiutchev, M. LermontovN. Minskii, I. Nikitin, and some folksongs.
  - Russia –- History (1879-1937), undated. (Box-folder 4: 7)
    Notes prepared by B. P. Lopatin on the revolutionary movement in Russia, especially the revolutions of 1905 and 1917.
  - Russian and Soviet Art and Architecture, 1937-1939 and undated. (Box-folder 4: 8)
    Clippings from Moscow News and Soviet Russia Today
  - Russian Literature, 1937-1938 and undated. (Box-folder 4: 9)
    Clippings about Alexander Pushkin, Ivan Turgenev, Leo Tolstoy, Maxim Gorky and Leonid Leonov
  - Sayings, undated. (Box-folder 4: 10)
    Russian, French and other sayings collected by B. P. Lopatin
  - Soviet Poetry, undated. (Box-folder 4: 11)
    Clippings of verse about Lenin, Stalin and other subjects by Armenian, Buryat, Georgian, Kazakh, and Lezgin poets translated into Russian
  - Printed Matter,1932-1942 and undated (Box-folder 4)
    Issues of Soviet periodicals, a pamphlet by Maxim Gorky, as well as an illustration depicting the Kremlin, Red Square and St. Basil’s Cathedral
  - Gorky, Maxim. To American Intellectuals, New York, International Publishers, 1932 (International Pamphlets No. 28) (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - Iskusstvo. Incomplete issue from 1937 (pages 125-166) (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - Ogonek. Ezhenedel’nyi literaturno-khudozhestvennyi illiustrirovannyi zhurnal, 1942: No. 35 (30 Aug.) (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - Orlov, V. “U stien Kremlia / By the Walls of Kreml,” undated. An illustration depicting the Kremlin, Red Square and St. Basil’s Cathedral (Box-folder 4: 15)
- Photographs, 1940 and undated. (Box-folder 4: 16)
  One photograph of Agata Sergievna Lopatina and one photograph of Oleg Borisovich Lopatin, as well as a contact print of the decoration of a theatrical or movie set